Guide to the Records of The New York Institute for the Humanities RG.37.4
New York University Archives
- Series III: Audio Recordings, 67170
  - Subseries A: Cassette Tapes, 1974-2005; 67171
    - Meeting on Urban Development, with Saskia Sassen, Undated; cuid4144; 180527; 1 sound cassettes 36:16 (Box 72, Folder 38, Box Access 8, Item 17)
      This appears to be a recording of a meeting of people discussing urban development in New York City. Saskia Sassen-Koob is among the people present. The meeting closes by one of the participants listing a number of other groups in the City interested in urban issues and holding meetings in upcoming weeks.
      Access copy available on CD: ACCESS 8:17
      Community development, Urban; Sassen, Saskia
    - The Hebrew Political Poetry of Aharon Shabtai and English Translations by Peter Cole. Readings and discussion with the author and translator., Undated; cuid4145; 180529; 1 sound cassettes Approx 70 minutes (Box 72, Folder 39, Box Access 8, Item 18)
      Israeli poet Aharon Shabtai discusses political poetry. Peter Cole discusses translating the poems into English. Cole and Shabtai read the poems both in Hebrew and English and then discuss.
      Access copy available on CD: ACCESS 8:18
      Hebrew poetry; Israeli poetry; Hebrew poetry, Modern; Cole, Peter, 1957- Poems. Selections; Shabtai, Aharon. Poems. Selections. English; Protest poetry, Hebrew; Cole, Peter, 1957-; Shabtai, Aharon
    - Harvard GSD (Graduate School of Design) Conference. Talks by Moshe Safdie, Teddy Kollek, and Richard Sennet, Undated; cuid4146; 180530; 1 sound cassettes Approx 60 minutes (Box 72, Folder 40, Box Access 8, Item 19)
      Three talks by various speakers at the Harvard Graduate School of Design Conference of an unknown year. Talks by Moshe Safdie, Teddy Kollek and Richard Sennett.
      Access copy available on CD: ACCESS 8:19
    - Discussion of the Equal Rights Amendment of 1972. New Right Seminar., Undated; cuid4147; 180534; 1 sound cassettes (Box 72, Folder 41, Box Access 8, Item 20, Item 21)
      Barbara Ehrenreich and Allen Hunter act as "co-conveners" of this New Right Seminar on the Equal Rights Amendment of 1972 and how the political right reacted to it.
      Access copy available on 2 CDs: ACCESS 8:20 and ACCESS 8:21
      Equal rights amendments; Conservatism; New Right; Hunter, Allen, 1944-; Ehrenreich, Barbara
    - Untitled Lecture by Richard Rorty, Undated; cuid4148; 180535; 1 sound cassettes Approx 80 minutes (Box 72, Folder 42, Box Access 8, Item 22)
      Access copy available on CD: ACCESS 8:22
      Richard Rorty talks for 78 minutes, discussing, among other things, truth, knowledge, science, values, ethics, moral philosophy language and human cognitive capacity.
      Rorty, Richard
    - Einstein and Religion Biography Seminar, Undated; cuid4149; 180536; 1 sound cassettes (Box 72, Folder 43, Box Access 8, Item 23)
      Access copy available on CD: ACCESS 8:23
      Unidentified speaker discusses Albert Einstein and religion, followed by Q&A. The title of the talk seems to be based on the Einstein quote, "The Lord God is subtle, but malicious he is not."
      Astrophysics; Mathematical physics; Physics |x Social aspects.; Physics -- Study and teaching -- United States; Religion.; Spinoza, Benedictus de, 1632-1677; Einstein, Albert, 1879-1955
    - The Use of Narrative in Historical Writing. A Conversation with Tom Bender, Undated; cuid4150; 180538; 1 sound cassettes (Box 72, Folder 45, Box Access 8, Item 24)
      Thomas Bender leads a conversation (and Q&A) about the use of narrative in historical writing. He bases his talk on the relationship between the history of cities and cultural history.
      Access copy available on CD: ACCESS 8:24
      narrative structure; Writing history; Bender, Thomas
    - Authority Conference: A Three-Day Discourse on Production and the Division of Labor., Feb. 24-26, 1978; cuid4151; 180541; 4 sound cassettes Approx. 6 hours (Box 72, Folder 46, Box Access 8, Item 25, Item 26)
      Historical note
      The Authority Conference brought approximately 20 humanistic scholars together in order to discuss authority, production, and the division of labor and how those topics are treated in thought, theory, and practice in various humanities fields. Intellectual goals stated in a letter of invitation were to better "understand how the productive processes of modern society are changing in ways not anticipated in past social theory" and to "expand the meaning of the term 'production' itself, so that it appears as a cultural, psychological, and epistemological category as well as a category in political economy." The final desired outcome of the conference was to set up an ongoing working group to pursue whatever develops during the sessions.
      Session 1: "The Production of Meaning" lead by Anthony Giddens and Bernard Williams. Session 2: "The Economic and Psychological Conflicts in the Division of Labor" lead by Dick Sennett and Bob Solow. Session 3: TAPES MISSING "On Emerging Conflicts in Patterns of Authority in Modern Capitalism" lead by Claus Offe and Elizabeth Hegeman, summarized by Alessandro Pizzorno. Session 4: PART 1 MISSING - Conference Wrap Up/Next Steps.
      Session 1.1: ACCESS 11:06 Session 1.2: ACCESS 11:07 Session 1.3: ACCESS 8:26 Session 2.1: ACCESS 8:25 Session 2.2-2.3: ACCESS 10:02 Session 3.1-3.3: TAPES MISSING - NO ACCESS COPY Session 4.1: TAPE MISSING - NO ACCESS COPY Session 4.2-4.3: ACCESS 8:30
      Authority; Division of labor; Economic development.; Capitalism.; Production control; Production functions (Economic theory); Labor supply.; Ford Foundation; Hirschman, Albert O.; Gendlin, Eugene T., 1926-; Giddens, Anthony; Hegeman, Elizabeth; Kohn, Melvin L., 1928-; Morgenbesser, Sidney, 1921-2004; Nagel, Thomas, 1937-; Offe, Claus; Piore, Michael J.; Bickford, Jane; Williams, Bernard, 1929-2003; Zuboff, Shoshana, 1951-; Solow, Robert M.; Unger, Roberto Mangabeira; Skinner, Quentin; Smith, Jonathan Z.; Schrank, Robert, 1917-; Sennett, Richard, 1943-; Rollings, Andrew E.; Sabel, Charles F.; Berger, Suzanne E., 1944-; Pizzorno, Alessandro; Frampton, Kenneth; Birnbaum, Norman; Garfinkel, Harold; Freidson, Eliot, 1923-2005
    - Equality, Opportunity and Capability. A discussion with Amartya Sen., Undated; cuid4152; 180542; 1 sound cassettes Approx. 90 minutes (Box 72, Folder 47, Box Access 8, Item 27, Item 28)
      Amartya Sen discusses freedom, equality, opportunity and capability.
      Access copy available on 2 CDs: ACCESS 8:27 and ACCESS 8:28
      Opportunity; capability; Equality; Freedom; Sen, Amartya, 1933-
    - Youth, Race, and Poverty: On Downward Mobility in America. A Lecture by William Finnegan, April 5, 1996; cuid4153; 180543; 1 sound cassettes Approx 65 minutes (Box 72, Folder 48, Box Access 8, Item 29)
      Access copy available on CD: ACCESS 8:29
      New York Times staff writer William Finnegan discusses the topic of a book in progress - youth, race and poverty in America and the trend of downward mobility. Before Finnegan's lecture, Charles Halpern eulogizes W. Hayword Burns, who had been killed in an automobile accident the previous Tuesday.
      Children of minorities; Youth with social disabilities; Youth.; downward mobility; Poverty.; Ethnic groups.; Finnegan, William
    - Gustave Flaubert Discussion Group, Approximately 1972-1982; cuid4154; 180545; 1 sound cassettes Approx. 90 minutes (Box 72, Folder 50)
      This is a recording of a discussiong group engaging in conversation about the works of Gustave Flaubert, focusing on A Sentimental Education in particular. The recording begins without introduction or preamble. The first several minutes are people arriving and chatting. The only person to be identified in the recording, by way of being greeted is a man hailed as "Professor Falk." The discussion begins at about 9:50, with one participant reading a passage from Sentimental Education.
      Access copy available on 2 CDs: ACCESS 9:50 & ACCESS 9:51.
      Flaubert, Gustave, 1821-1880. Education sentimentale. English; Flaubert, Gustave, 1821-1880
    - The Philosophy of Karl Popper. A Conversation with Jonathan Lieberson, Probably 1982-1983; cuid4155; 180546; 1 sound cassettes 20:19 (Box 72, Folder 51)
      Scholar and author Jonathan Lieberson discusses the philosophy of Karl Popper, focusing on, among other topics, objectivity vs. subjectivity, reification and subjective investments.
      Access copy available on CD: ACCESS 9:52
      Philosophy; Popper, Karl R. (Karl Raimund), 1902-1994; Lieberson, Jonathan
    - Post-911 Israeli/Palestinian Relations, Probably March 2003; cuid4156; 180548; 1 sound cassettes Approx 90 minutes (Box 72, Folder 52)
      Access copy available on 2 CDs: ACCESS 9:53 & ACCESS 9:54
      The moderator introduces the speaker as "Nissim," the author of five books and the editor of a Hebrew critical journal. The speaker is likely Nissim Mishal, a prominent Israeli author and journalist. The discussion is of the Middle East within the post-911 political/military/social sphere. Particular focus is put upon the relationship and forced intimacy between Israelis and pPalestinians in the 18 months following the September 11 attacks.
      Israel |x Arabs.; Israel; United States |x Foreign relations |z Israel; Mishal, Nissim, 1949-
    - People, Technology, Literature. A lecture by Richard Poirier, November 4, 1982; cuid4157; 180549; 1 sound cassettes 34:13 (Box 72, Folder 53)
      Author and literary critic Richard Poirier delivers a lecture entitled "People, Technology, Literature" or "If they don't buy the appliance, give them the literature." He discusses technology as an instrument of loss in literature. The recording starts without introduction or preamble.
      Access copy available on CD: ACCESS 10:1
      American literature -- 20th century.; Literature.; Technology.; English literature.; Literature/literary criticism; Poirier, Richard
    - Racial Rival as American Ritual. A Conversation with Derrick Bell, February 1996; cuid4158; 180553; 1 sound cassettes Approx. 70 minutes (Box 72, Folder 55)
      After introductions from the audience, the moderator briefly eulogizes poet Joseph Brodsky, a founding member of NYIH, who had passed away the previous week. She reads a statement about him and this is followed by one more short eulogy of him entitled "In Remembrance of Joseph Brodsky, Institute Fellow," written by Carl Schorske and read by Jerry Seigel. Derrick Bell is the primary speaker, beginning his talk about 8 minutes into the recording. Professor Bell speaks briefly and generally about the subject "racial rival as American ritual" and engages with the audience.
      Access copy available on CD: ACCESS 10:3
      Race discrimination.; Race relations.; Race discrimination -- United States.; Race relations -- United States.; Race.; American poetry -- 20th century.; Schorske, Carl E.; Bell, Derrick A., 1930-2011; Seigel, Jerrold E.; Brodsky, Joseph, 1940-1996
    - The Future of the United States Aerospace Industry. A Lecture by Neil deGrasse Tyson, Probably 2002; cuid4159; 180554; 1 sound cassettes Approx. 57 minutes (Box 72, Folder 56)
      Access copy available on CD: ACCESS 10:4
      Neil DeGrasse Tyson discusses his work on the Commission on the Future of the United States Aerospace Industry and the report the Commission produced, entitled "Anyone, Anything, Anywhere, Anytime." The commission sought to find the reasons behind the decline in the American aerospace industry and suggestions on how to reverse the negative trend.
      aerospace industry; Tyson, Neil deGrasse; Commission on the Future of the United States Aerospace Industry
    - Readings and Discussion with Poet John Hollander, Probably mid-1980s; cuid4160; 180555; 1 sound cassettes Approx 80 minutes (Box 72, Folder 57)
      Access copy available on 2 CDs: ACCESS 10:5 and ACCESS 10:6.
      John Hollander, reads recent (some unpublished) short poetry and invites the audience to ask questions and and spark discussion between poems.
      American poetry -- 20th century.; Poetry.; Hollander, John. Poems. Selections; American poetry -- 20th century -- History and criticism.; Hollander, John
    - "Kid Culture," A Sexuality, Gender and Consumerism Seminar talk by David Nasaw (Tape 2), Undated; cuid4161; 180556; 1 sound cassettes 18:37 (Box 72, Folder 58)
      Access copy available on CD: ACCESS 10:7
      Recording is the last 18 minutes of David Nasaw's "Sexuality, Gender, and Consumerism Seminar" discussion on Kid Culture. He discusses middle class verus working class children in the early 20th century, focusing on childrens roles in newspaper sales and home delivery.
    - Current Practice in Law School Education. A Discussion with David A.J. Richards and others, February 12, 1986; cuid4162; 180559; 1 sound cassettes Approx. 47 minutes (Box 72, Folder 60)
      Discussion and criticism of current practice in law school education. One speaker is NYU Professor of Law David A.J. Burns; the other is identified on the tape label only as "Burns." In the course of conversation it is learned that he attended Yale Law School in the 1960s.
      Access copy available on CD: ACCESS 10:24
      Law schools -- United States.; Law teachers -- Cambridge (Mass.); Lawyer.; New York University. School of Law.; Law -- Study and teaching -- United States.; Law |x Study and teaching.; Law -- United States.; Law.; Richards, David A.J.
    - Lecture on post-911 Military Action by Richard Falk, Around 2002 - 2003; cuid4163; 180562; 1 sound cassettes Approx. 90 minutes (Box 72, Folder 62)
      Prolific writer on issues of war, legal theory, and global relations, Richard Falk discusses the current situation in American conflicts in the Arab world. He also discusses the controversy he encountered after publishing a piece in The Nation, in which he endorsed a military response against the Taliban in Afganistan in response to the terrorist attacks of September 11, 2001.
      Access copy available on 2 CDs: ACCESS 10:9 & ACCESS 10:10
      September 11 Terrorist Attacks, 2001.; Afghan War, 2001-; Falk, Richard A., 1930-
    - Necessity, Validity and Opportunities of Culturally Specific Institutions. A Lecture by Thelma Golden, Around 2000-2010; cuid4164; 180565; 1 sound cassettes Approx. 60 minutes (Box 72, Folder 63)
      Access copy available on CD: ACCESS 10:11
      Thelma Golden poses and discusses the question, "What is the necessity, validity and opportunities for a culturally specific institution?" Depending on the year of this recording, Golden is speaking either as the Deputy Director for Exhibitions and Programs (2000-2005) or Director and President (2005-present) of the Studio Museum in Harlem.
      African American art museum curators; African American art.; Harlem (New York, N.Y.); Golden, Thelma; Studio Museum in Harlem
    - Breaking Open the Head. A discussion with Daniel Pinchbeck about his recent book., 22-Nov-02; cuid4165; 180571; 1 sound cassettes Approx. 60 minutes (Box 72, Folder 64)
      Access copy available on CD: ACCESS 10:12
      Open City founding editor Daniel Pinchbeck discusses his recently published book, Breaking Open the Head. The book explores Pinchbeck's experimentation of psychodelic drugs and world travels, cultural criticism, and philosophy. Q&A after about 35 minutes.
      Literature/literary criticism; Literature.; Avant-garde literature.; American literature -- 21st century; Pinchbeck, Daniel
    - Travels with Herodotus. A Discussion with Ryszard Kapuscinski, Probably 2004; cuid4166; 180574; 1 sound cassettes Approx. 60 minutes (Box 72, Folder 65)
      Access copy available on CD: ACCESS 10:13
      Ryszard Kapuscinski discusses his work writing about Herodotus. Asked to write a textbook on journalistic reportage, Kapuscinski decided to do it through the lens of an examination of Herodotus, whom he considers to be the best author of reportage in history. The discussion is on Herodotus as the first globalist and his understanding that in order to understand one's own culture's history, one must also try to understand the history of other cultures as well. The book, Travels with Herodotus, was published in 2004.
      Literature |x History and criticism.; History.; History |x Study and teaching.; History and criticism.; Writing history; Greek history; Travel journalism; Journalism; Reportage literature; Herodotus; Kapuściński, Ryszard, 1932-2007
    - European Response to September 11. A Lecture by Jane Kramer, Early 2002; cuid4167; 180575; 1 sound cassettes Approx. 90 minutes (Box 72, Folder 66)
      Access copy available on CD: ACCESS 10:14 & ACCESS 10:15
      European correspondent for the New Yorker, Jane Kramer discusses the European response to September 11 from both historical and contemporary aspects.
      New Yorker (New York, N.Y.: 1925); September 11 Terrorist Attacks, 2001.; Kramer, Jane
    - Translating the Poetry of Eugenio Montale. A Discussion with Jonathan Galassi, 2002; cuid4168; 180577; 1 sound cassettes Approx. 56 minutes (Box 72, Folder 67)
      President and Publisher of Farrar, Straus and Giroux, Jonathan Galassi discusses the life and poetry of Eugenio Montale, and his own work in translating those poems into English.
      Access copy available on CD: ACCESS 10:16
      Lyric poetry; Poetry -- Translating; Italian poetry; Poetry.; Galassi, Jonathan; Montale, Eugenio, 1896-1981
    - A Warning About Good Things. A Discussion with David Rieff, 2002; cuid4169; 180579; 2 sound cartridges Approx. 90 minutes (Box 72, Folder 68)
      David Rieff presents a thumbnail sketch the humanitatrian emergencies such as wars and disasters he has witnessed and written about over the last 10 years. Recently dubbed "Mr. Pessimism" by Time magazine, Rieff tries to offer, not so much pessimism, but "a warning about good things." He argues against the dangerous assumption that "all good things go together."
      Access copy available on CD: ACCESS 10:17 & ACCESS 10:18.
      War stories, Bosnian; Sarajevo (Bosnia and Hercegovina); Humanitarian assistance; Humanitarianism; Rieff, David
    - Media Unlimited: How the Torrent of Images and Sounds Overwhelms Our Lives. A Conversation with Todd Gitlin, 2002; cuid4170; 180581; 1 sound cassettes Approx. 46 minutes (Box 72, Folder 70)
      Todd Gitlin speaks on the subject of his new book, Media Unlimited: How the Torrent of Images and Sounds Overwhelms Our Lives.
      Access copy available on CD: ACCESS 10:19
      Mass media.; Internet |z United States.; Gitlin, Todd
    - Discussion on Writing with Novelist Jennifer Egan, 2002; cuid4171; 180582; 1 sound cassettes Approx. 60 minutes (Box 72, Folder 71)
      Writer Jennifer Egan discusses her writing process and several of her novels, the most recent of which, Look At Me, published on September 18, 2001, was about Muslim terrorism with a protagonist errily similar to Mohammad Atta, one of the ringleaders and hijackers of teh September 11 attacks.
      Access copy available on CD: ACCESS 10:20.
      Writing; September 11 Terrorist Attacks, 2001.; Fiction.; Egan, Jennifer; Atta, Mohamed, 1968-2001
    - The Importance of Truth and Reconciliation. A Lecture by Albie Sachs, February, 2002; cuid4172; 180583; 1 sound cassettes Approx. 60 minutes (Box 72, Folder 72)
      Access copy available on CD: ACCESS 10:21
      Activist and a former African National Congress lawyer and Constitutional Court of South Africa Judge Albie Sachs focuses mainly on the importance and success of Truth and Reconciliation Commissions and how the South African Commission may be looked at as a model. He also discusses Apartheid, his imprisonment, and the failed assassination attempt that took one of his arms.
      South Africa; Apartheid; Sachs, Albie, 1935- Jail diary of Albie Sachs; African National Congress; South Africa. Truth and Reconciliation Commission; South Africa. Constitutional Court; Sachs, Albie, 1935-
    - The Depiction of Clothing in Painting Throughout History. A Lecture by Anne Hollander, Probably 2002; cuid4173; 180588; 1 sound cassettes Approx. 70 minutes (Box 72, Folder 73)
      Access copy available on CD: ACCESS 10:22
      Art Historian, Anne Hollander takes her audience through a history of garments and depictions of clothing in art - going through Grecian works, biblical oil paintings, Rennaissance works and many other styles and eras.
      Art, Renaissance; Fashion; Painting, Renaissance; Fashion in art; Buonarroti, Michelangelo, 1475-1564
    - Screening and Discussion with Bill Morrison About his Found Footage Film, Decasia, November 2002; cuid4174; 180589; 1 sound cassettes Approx. 60 minutes (Box 72, Folder 74)
      This is a screening of part of the 2002 film Decasia and discussion with the filmmaker, Bill Morrison. After 10 minutes of introductory remarks, 10:20 -27:15 is just music, being audio from the film. The remaining half hour is a discussion between the audience and Morrison. Decasia was created entirely out of found footage and is intended to be a mediation on the loss and decay of old films. The film features an original score by Michael Gordon.
      Access copy available on CD: ACCESS 10:23
      Silent films; Gordon, Michael, 1956- Decasia; Film.; filmmaking; Films.; Stock footage; Film materials.; Film composers.; Avant-garde films.; Acetate film |z 16mm.; Acetate film |v 8mm |v Super 8.; Morrison, Bill, 1965 November 17-; Gordon, Michael, 1956-
    - Hawthorne: A Life - A Discussion on the Man and the Biography, with Author Brenda Wineapple., September 26, probably 2003; cuid4175; 180590; 1 sound cassettes Approx. 60 minutes (Box 72, Folder 75, Box Access 10, Item 35)
      Access copy available on CD: ACCESS 10:35
      Scope and contents
      Brenda Wineapple discusses the life of Nathaniel Hawthorne and her latest book, which is about him.
      Hawthorne, Nathaniel, 1804-1864; Wineapple, Brenda
    - Contemporary Chinese Culture, Economics, and Politics. A Lecture by Peter Kwong, probably 2003; cuid4176; 180595; 1 sound cassettes Approx. 63 minutes (Box 72, Folder 77, Box Access 10, Item 36)
      Scholar and documentary filmmaker Peter Kwong discusses contemporary Chinese politics, economics, and society, focusing on the governments recent acceptance of certain capitalistic practices, while maintaining a communistic regime.
      Access copy available on CD: ACCESS 10:36
      Chinese.; China |x Foreign relations |y 1976-; Kwong, Peter
    - Every Exit is an Entrance: A Praise of Sleep. Readings and Discussion with Poet Anne Carson, 21-Feb-03; cuid4177; 180597; 1 sound cassettes Approx. 65 minutes (Box 72, Folder 78, Box Access 10, Item 37)
      Poet Anne Carson reads and discusses her work, focusing on a poem "Every Exit is an Entrance: A Praise of Sleep," which would be published two years later in 2005 as part of the collection of her work entitled, Decreation.
      Access copy available on CD: ACCESS 10:37
      Poets, American.; American poetry -- 21st century; American poetry -- 20th century.; Poetry.; Carson, Anne, 1950 December 16-
    - Discussion with Argentine Legal Scholar and Moral Philosopher, Carlos Santiago Nino, Around 1985-88; cuid4178; 180598; 1 sound cassettes Approx. 90 minutes (Box 72, Folder 79)
      Access copy available on 2 CDs: ACCESS 11:04 and ACCESS 11:05
      In the 1980s, Carlos Santiago Nino was assistant to Argentine President Raúl Alfonsín and active as chair of the Council for the Consolidation of Democracy (Consejo para la Consolidación de la Democracia) in Argentina and became assistant to the president of that country. He was a legal scholar and moral philosopher. In this talk he discusses Argentina's upheaval through moral and legal lenses.
      Ethics; Argentina.; Nino, Carlos Santiago; Consejo para la Consolidación de la Democracia (Argentina)